[Music]
What's new in financial reporting in
Business Central 2025 release wave 1 for
administrators? In this wave, you get
two new features and then I'm going to
show you some new documentation for
auditing. So you get telemetry on usage
and life cycle changes to to
definitions. You get the same in
Microsoft Purview. I don't have a demo
for it. I'll just mention that here. And
then there's some new documentation as I
said on how to set up audit changes to
report definitions with change lock and
also how um to set up permissions both
for a authoring and for using financial
reports. So let's dive into business
central and see that.
So imagine you have a finance user and
um a user that use finance reporting all
the time. There are two types of users
here. One type of user we call the
author. The author can uh likely edit uh
report row column definitions and
similarly do actions such as copying,
exporting, importing both for row uh
report definitions but also for row
definitions and column definitions. So
in order for you to track if you have
requirements where it's important that
you track changes to report definitions
uh we now have the ability to see this
in in in telemetry for the environment
and similarly not only for the author
but also for users of of um financial
reports. Whenever users view a report or
they print a report to PDF or if they
open a report with an Excel layout, all
of this is also locked. So all the usage
of financial reports are also logged to
telemetry. So you can see who ran which
reports and with the author you can see
who changed which report uh report
definitions when. So let's dive into uh
to to see that in just a few examples in
Azure applications
insights. All right. So here in
application insights, let me just try to
query the last 30 days of of traces
where the message has financial in the
name. There are of course real event ids
that you can use. So you should never
just use the message as I do it for
illustration purposes. I'm just doing
that. And here um you can see some of
the different types of events that I
talked about when I was in business
central. For instance, I can see that a
certain financial report was run on
screen and this is the code Russ Vaja
whatever that report is. We also get
some life cycle telemetry here um of a
report being created. Some different
reports being created. These are the
report definition codes and uh similarly
report column definitions were created
here. If I expand this a bit, you can
see the code of these. So that means
that you in telemetry now have depending
on your retention policy of telemetry
you have
um events that show both the usage of
financial reports as well as changes to
financial
reports. So that was uh the telemetry
part. Now the similar type of events
will eventually surface in Microsoft
purview. Business central in uh data in
Microsoft purview is uh in currently in
preview. Um but uh these changes to
financial reports definitions will also
appear in your Microsoft purview
instance. Then I mentioned two things
about being able to track with change
lock. Um that's new so new
documentation. So let's switch to the to
the business central documentation for
financial report and I'll show you the
new
documentation. So here in Microsoft
learn there's a new article for auditing
and I'll just uh simply search for
audits here and immediately I get the
first search result audit changes to
financial reporting. Let's have a look.
So this new article tells you as an ad
administrator what are the report uh
definition tables. What are the tables
behind report row and column
definitions? And these are the table
numbers that you need to set up change
log for financial report definition
changes. I'm not going to demo the
change lock feature here. I'm sure you
can do that. If you are uh if you want
even more um security around or auditing
around your financial report
definitions, you can you can use the
deluxe version of change log which is
called
um which is called uh sensitive field
monitoring. Um, so if you set up that,
you will both get change log, but you
also have the ability to get email
notifications if someone changes a value
for that. Another thing this article
shows is how to analyze your changes to
financial report definitions with the
data analysis feature. And uh let me
just quickly show you that if if you
take the change lock page into analysis
mode, you now have a way to pivot this
data either which definition changed or
the other way around who changed what
and when. So you can either put yourself
in the in the context of a user changing
and see who what they did can it change
or you can you can go in and see who has
been working on the report definitions
for uh the income statement. The final
part of this documentation is what are
the permissions to view or edit reports.
You might know but now this is also part
of the financial reporting
documentation. So you can easily see the
permission sets either for viewing or
editing financial reports. Now while we
are in docs or in in the documentation
two new articles I think might be of
interest for you as an administrator.
The first article is about
troubleshooting financial reporting in
case you need to help an author. There's
some guidance here. So maybe it doesn't
work and maybe there are uh some advice
here that can help that author get
unblocked. And finally, we added also an
FAQ, a frequently asked question page
for financial reporting with at least
the the most recently quest or frequent
quest questions we get on the feature.
And maybe this can also be of help for
you to unblock uh the the the authors uh
among your users. So that's what we have
for the administrator in financial
reporting.